<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!--
This file is Copyright (c) 2010 by the GPSD project
BSD terms apply: see the file COPYING in the distribution root for details.
-->
<!DOCTYPE refentry PUBLIC 
   "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
   "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd">
<refentry id='gpsdecode.1'>
<refentryinfo><date>13 Jul 2005</date></refentryinfo>
<refmeta>
<refentrytitle>gpsdecode</refentrytitle>
<manvolnum>1</manvolnum>
<refmiscinfo class="source">The GPSD Project</refmiscinfo>
<refmiscinfo class="manual">GPSD Documentation</refmiscinfo>
</refmeta>
<refnamediv id='name'>
<refname>gpsdecode</refname>
<refpurpose>decode GPS, RTCM or AIS streams into a readable format</refpurpose>
</refnamediv>
<refsynopsisdiv id='synopsis'>

<cmdsynopsis>
  <command>gpsdecode</command>  
      <arg choice='opt'>-c</arg>
      <arg choice='opt'>-d</arg>
      <arg choice='opt'>-e</arg>
      <arg choice='opt'>-j</arg>
      <arg choice='opt'>-t <replaceable>typelist</replaceable></arg>
      <arg choice='opt'>-u</arg>
      <arg choice='opt'>-v</arg>
      <arg choice='opt'>-D <replaceable>debuglevel</replaceable></arg>
      <arg choice='opt'>-V</arg>
</cmdsynopsis>
</refsynopsisdiv>

<refsect1 id='description'><title>DESCRIPTION</title>

<para>This tool is a batch-mode decoder for NMEA and various binary
packet formats associated with GPS, AIS, and differential-correction
services.  It produces a JSON dump on standard output from binary on
standard input. The JSON is the same format documented in
<citerefentry><refentrytitle>gpsd</refentrytitle><manvolnum>8</manvolnum></citerefentry>;
this tool uses the same decoding logic as gpsd, but with a simpler
interface intended for batch processing of data files.</para>

<para>All sensor-input formats known to the GPSD project can be
decoded by this tool.  These include: NMEA, AIVDM (the NMEA-derived
sentence format used by AIS, the marine Automatic Identification
System), RTCM2, and all supported GPS binary formats (notably
including SiRF). See
<citerefentry><refentrytitle>gpsd</refentrytitle><manvolnum>8</manvolnum></citerefentry>
for applicable standards and known limitations of the decoding
logic.</para>

<para>You can use this tool with
<citerefentry><refentrytitle>nc</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></citerefentry>
to examine AIS feeds from AIS pooling services, RTCM feeds from RTCM
receivers or NTRIP broadcasters.</para>

</refsect1>
<refsect1 id='options'><title>OPTIONS</title>

<para>The <option>-d</option> option tells the program to decode
packets presented on standard input to standard output. This is the
default behavior.</para>

<para>The <option>-j</option> explicitly sets the output dump format
to JSON (the default behavior).</para>

<para>The <option>-e</option> option option tells the program to
encode JSON on standard input to JSON on standard output. This option
is only useful for regression-testing of the JSON dumping and parsing
code.</para>

<para>The <option>-t</option> accepts a comma-separated list of
numeric types.  Packets with a numeric AIS, RTCM2, or RTCM3 type are
passed through and output only if they match a type in the
list. Packets of other kinds (in particular GPS packets) are
passed through unconditionally.</para>

<para>The <option>-u</option> suppresses scaling of AIS data to float
quantities and text expansion of numeric codes.  A dump with this
option is lossless.</para>

<para>The <option>-v</option> enables dumping of textual packets
to output as they are received on input, immediately preceding 
corresponding output.</para>

<para>The <option>-c</option> sets the AIS dump format to separate
fields with an ASCII pipe symbol.  Fields are dumped in the order they
occur in the AIS packet. Numerics are not scaled (-u is
forced). Strings are unpacked from six-bit to full ASCII</para>

<para>The <option>-V</option> option directs the program to emit its
version number, then exit.</para>

<para>The <option>-D</option> option sets a debug verbosity level.  It is
mainly of interest to developers.</para>

</refsect1>
<refsect1 id='json_ais'><title>AIS DSV FORMAT</title> 

<para>With the <option>-c</option> option, dump lines are values of AIS
payload fields, pipe-separated, in the order that they occur in the
payload. Spans of fields expressing a date are emitted as an ISO8601
timestamp (look for colons and the trailing Z indicating Zulu/UTC
time), and the 19-bit group of TDMA status fields found at the end of
message types 1-4 are are dumped as a single unsigned integer (in hex
preceded by "0x"). Unused regional-authority fields are also dumped
(in hex preceded by "0x"). Variable-length binary fields are dumped as
an integer bit length, followed by a colon, followed by a hex
dump.</para>

</refsect1>
<refsect1 id='see_also'><title>SEE ALSO</title>
<para>
<citerefentry><refentrytitle>gpsd</refentrytitle><manvolnum>8</manvolnum></citerefentry>,
<citerefentry><refentrytitle>gpsctl</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></citerefentry>,
<citerefentry><refentrytitle>gpsdctl</refentrytitle><manvolnum>8</manvolnum></citerefentry>,
<citerefentry><refentrytitle>gps</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></citerefentry>,
<citerefentry><refentrytitle>libgps</refentrytitle><manvolnum>3</manvolnum></citerefentry>,
<citerefentry><refentrytitle>libgpsd</refentrytitle><manvolnum>3</manvolnum></citerefentry>,
<citerefentry><refentrytitle>gpsprof</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></citerefentry>,
<citerefentry><refentrytitle>gpsfake</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum></citerefentry>,
</para>
</refsect1>
<refsect1 id='maintainer'><title>AUTHOR</title> 

<para>Eric S. Raymond <email>esr@thyrsus.com</email>.</para>
</refsect1>

</refentry>
